And at the first blush of the oak leaves,
當樹葉開始從綠色變紅色 我們就搬去格羅夫
The only trouble is there's a hundred perils between here and there.
唯一的問題是那裡到處都有威脅
I'm peril.
我是威脅
-Stop!
停下來
Our light is fading.
我們的光，正漸漸消逝
And this  mithril... It is our only salvation?
這個秘銀… 真的是我們唯一的救贖？
So the fate of the entire Elven race...
所以全精靈族的命運…
-...is in your hands. -Hmm.
掌握在你的手裡
Nampat!
戰鬥！
Sauron was once your people's enemy as much as mine.
索倫曾是你們的敵人，就跟我一樣
I call on you to reforge the alliance
我呼籲妳重建努曼諾爾 和精靈之間的聯盟
To save the men of the Southlands.
拯救南地人
Give it to me.
給我
It's under here.
在這下面
All hail to the true King of the Southlands.
向南方大地真正的國王致敬
All hail!
致敬！
Take shelter!
找掩護！
The Queen!
女王！
Theo!
西奧！
Help!
救命！
Halbrand!
賀爾布蘭！
Elendil!
伊蘭迪爾！
Mother? Mother?
母親？
Mother!
母親！
Over here.
這裡
Come here.
過來
-Are you hurt? -No.
–你有受傷嗎？ –沒有
Stay with me.
跟著我
Come on.
來
Crawl. I won't leave you.
快爬，我不會丟下你
Soldier, over here!
士兵，這裡！
Valandil.
維蘭迪爾
Soldier, he's gone.
士兵，他走了
He's gone.
他走了
This way!
走吧！
-He's gone... -Come on!
–他走了… –快啊！
-Help! Please, help! -Soldiers!
拜託，救救我們！
Over here! We're inside!
士兵，屋頂要塌了
-Can't get out! -Quickly, clear a path.
快，開出一條路來
Over here. This way.
這裡，這邊
Take hold of my hand. You're all right.
握住我的手，沒事的
Go forward. Stay together.
往前走，別走散了
-Hurry, my Queen. -Go.
女王，快
Go towards the bridge.
往橋的方向走
Get them out of here!
快把他們救出來！
Isildur!
伊西鐸！
Old Bolgerbuck went snailing
老皮革哥抓蝸牛去
One autumn day so fine
秋高氣爽好天氣
He found a hundred big ones
他抓到一百隻大蝸牛
I wish that they were mine
如果是我的就好了
Up ahead.
前面
The Grove! I think this is it.
格羅夫！到了到了
Said that three days ago.
你三天前也這麼說
No, no, he's right. I remember this.
他這次沒說錯，我記得這個
Come on.
加油
Do you smell that? Wood smoke! The others must've started bakin'.
聞到沒？燒木頭的煙味！ 其他人肯定開始生火燒烤了
Mr. Burrows.
布羅斯先生
What happened?
這是怎麼回事？
My great-grand used to speak of mountains to the south that could spit fire-rock.
我曾祖父曾提過 南方有山會噴出岩漿
He said they go to sleep.
他說這種山會休眠
Sometimes for hundreds of years.
有時長達數百年
Only to wake again when a new evil is rising.
只有在新的邪惡勢力崛起時 才會再甦醒
-Hmm. -Brandyfoot.
白蘭地足
Your friend up there. The big fella.
妳那個朋友，那大塊頭
-You don't suppose... -Suppose what?
–妳不是該… –該怎樣？
Maybe he could fix it.
說不定他能扭轉這一切
-Go on, Nori. -Yes. Like he fixed those wolves.
–去問問，諾瑞 –就像扭轉狼群事件一樣
-Uh, I don't know... I don't know if he... -What you waitin' for?
–還在等什麼？ –這樣好嗎…
He's done so much for us.
他為我們做了那麼多
It's a mite rude of us to ask more of him.
得寸進尺有點不太禮貌
I see.
好吧
-I'll ask him, then.
我去問
Sadoc!
薩道克！
Out the way, little ones.
別擋路，小鬼頭
Á keuta...
重生…
Á envinyata...
修復…
Lótë na...
綻放…
-Lótë na... -What's he mutterin'?
–綻放… –他在喃喃自語什麼？
Likely little words, so the tree'll understand.
可能是簡單的詞語 這樣樹木才聽得懂
Sadoc, trees don't talk.
薩道克，樹木不會講話
Some do.
有些會
Envinyata!
修復吧！
Lótë na!
綻放吧！
Great-goats. It's working...
媽啊，真的有用
Á kuita! Á kuita! Á kuita!
重生吧！
He's fixin' it.
他成功了
Just like Sadoc said he would.
薩道克說的沒錯
-No! -Nori!
–不要！ –諾瑞！
My sweet girls! My babies!
我的小寶貝，寶貝女兒！
Nori! Dilly! Dilly.
諾瑞！迪莉！
Dilly, Nori, are you all right?
迪莉、諾瑞，還好嗎？
Are you all right?
沒事吧？
I'm all right. I said.
沒事，我沒事
-I'm all...
我…
We ask for something sacred from this mountain.
我們請求這座山賜予神聖之物
And so we offer something sacred in return.
因此我們會獻上神聖之物作為回報
In exchange for access to your  mithril  mines,
為了換取你們的秘銀礦石
the Elves are prepared to furnish this city
精靈族預備為這座城市
with game, grain,
提供獵物、糧食
and timber from the elder forests of Eriador for the next five centuries.
以及來自伊利雅德古老森林的木柴 長達五百年
Five centuries?
五百年？
Quite a promise, if they can keep it...
這承諾可不得了 如果真能信守的話…
I never made a promise I didn't.
我從不做無法信守的承諾
I see you've learned a few words of stone-tongue.
看來你學了些矮人秘語
Impressive.
了不起
Tell me, why should we trust any Elf?
告訴我，我們憑什麼相信精靈族？
You should not.
是不該相信
But you can trust me.
但你們可以相信我
For I am no common Elf, but Elrond Half-elven.
因為我不是尋常的精靈 我是半精靈愛隆
And I see in Elves that which they cannot see in themselves.
我在精靈族身上看到 他們自己看不到的東西
That is why I stand before you now, alone...
這就是為何 我現在獨自站在你們面前…
Pleading.
懇求你們
For you to save my people.
拯救我的族人
Please, noble King. Help us.
高貴的國王，我請求您，幫幫我們
I will speak to my son now.
我要跟我兒子談談
What is to be your answer, Father?
父王，你打算怎麼答覆他？
It is said that when Aulë created our people,
傳說奧力在創造矮人時
he crafted us of two elements.
用了兩種元素
Fire and rock.
火焰和岩石
The rock that lives within us hungers for the eternal,
我們內心深處的岩石渴望著永恆
resisting the pull of time.
抗拒著時間的拉扯
But the fire embraces truth.
但火焰卻坦然面對真相
That all things must one day be consumed...
萬物終有時
-...and fade away to ash... -Father...
–終會化為灰燼 –父親…
We do not dig in earth that cannot support it.
我們不挖撐不住的土
-Delving into depths beyond the darkness.
不進入超越黑暗的深處
Tempting shadow, rock, and mine to bury us all beneath the mountain.
不招惹暗影、岩石和礦石 以免族人被埋在山底
I will not risk Dwarven lives
我不會拿矮人族的生命冒險
to help the Elves cheat death.
去幫助精靈族逃避滅亡
Cheat death?
逃避滅亡？
Father!
父王！
My friend is drowning,
我的摯友快淹死了
reaching for me to pull him to shore.
他伸出手要我拉他上岸
You expect me to swat his hand away
你要我揮開他的手
because you're afraid of a bloody rock fall?
就因為你害怕該死的山崩？
The fate of the Elves was decided many Ages ago.
精靈的命運在數個紀元前就已決定
By minds much wiser,
由那些比我們更有智慧
much farther-seeing than our own.
更能通曉未來的大能者所決定
Defy their will, and this entire kingdom might fall.
違背他們的旨意 可能招致整個矮人王國的毀滅
Perhaps the entire Middle-earth.
甚至是整個中土世界
I am sorry, my son.
抱歉了，我兒
But their time has come.
但他們大限已到
-Lice-bearded, uncaring, old fool!
滿鬍蝨蟲、沒血沒淚的糟老頭！
What if he's right?
萬一他是對的呢？
You're not thinking of lettin' this happen!
你不會眼睜睜看這種事發生吧！
You said the other Dwarf-lords were open to the proposal.
你說有其他矮人領主 願意考慮這個協議
If we reopen the mine ourselves,
我們可以自己重啟礦井
prove to them there's a safe way to gather  mithril,
向他們證明 有安全的方法可以開採秘銀
perhaps they'd make him listen.
或許他們可以說服他
Perhaps we could force your father's hand.
或許我們可以推你父親一把
He's more than just my father, Disa.
他不只是我的父親，蒂莎
He's our king.
他還是我們的國王
What kind of father would I be
我算哪門子父親
if I teach our children the will of a king
要是我教導我的孩子們 國王的旨意
should be counted as dross to be cast to the wind?
可以當成礦渣隨意棄置？
-All right, fine.
好吧
I shouldn't have said he had lice in his beard.
我不該說他滿鬍蝨蟲
-Or called him a fool. -Yeah.
–也不該叫他糟老頭 –是啦
No.
真的
No, I detest it when you heap slag on my mother.
我自己也討厭你講我母親壞話
Uh, well, in your mother's case, she actually does have lice in her...
說到妳母親，她的蝨蟲…
I'm joking. I'm joking.
開玩笑的啦
Don't suppose I can elbow you into staying for dinner?
我應該無法說服你留下來吃晚餐吧？
Gil-galad must be informed.
要趕快通知吉爾加拉德
And soon, he will no longer be a king, for there will no longer be a Lindon.
他的王位很快就會不保 因為林頓將不復存在
So this is goodbye, then?
那就是要說再見了？
We do not say goodbye.
我們不說再見的
-We say  namá... -Namárië.
–我們說納瑪… –納瑪利耶
It means more than simply "farewell."
不只是“再會”的意思
It means... "Go towards goodness."
而是，“願你向善而行”
Elrond!
愛隆！
Why'd they do this?
他們為什麼這麼做？
To make this their home.
佔地為家
Their Shadow Land.
他們的陰影之地
So we take it back, and drive them off.
那我們趕走他們，把這裡搶回來
We have neither position, nor reinforcement.
我們既沒陣地，也沒援軍
These lands are dead.
這片土地已死
We must rally to the living.
我們要召集生還之人
Or put steel down their throats!
或是拿利劍刺穿他們的喉嚨！
It is over.
都結束了
Not for me. I won't allow it!
門都沒有，我不接受！
We must!
只能接受！
We must.
只能接受
What are you so bothered about? It isn't your fault.
妳難過什麼？這又不是妳的錯
Yes, it is.
是我的錯
Keep moving. That's it.
繼續前進，就是這樣
Help those people at the back there.
幫忙後面那些人
Isildur?
伊西鐸？
-The Queen! -She's alive.
–是女王！ –她還活著
-Is she hurt? -Save us!
–我的女王 –她在這裡
-Is she all right?
–她還好嗎？ –我以為我們失去她了
My Queen.
女王
Take my horse.
請騎我的馬
Captain, you...
船長，你…
-Captain... -Where is he?
–船長… –他呢？
Where is my son?
我兒子呢？
They're dead, aren't they?
他們都死了，對吧？
Arondir. My friends. My...
亞隆迪爾、我朋友們，我…
My mother. Everyone.
我母親，所有人
What cannot be known hollows the mind. Fill it not with guesswork.
未知會讓人變得無知 不要胡亂猜測
Where are we even going?
我們現在要去哪？
Númenor set their camp upon that ridgeline,
努曼諾爾人紮營在那邊的山脊線上
beyond that far peak.
要越過遠方那座山頭
That is where they shall hie to, along with any survivors.
他們應該會跟生還者過去那裡
Your mother included.
包括你母親
And be wary. The Orcs will move in daylight now.
記得保持警戒 現在半獸人白天也能出來活動
I've killed Orcs before, you know.
我殺過半獸人
When I was your age, there was no such thing as Orcs.
我在你這年紀 根本沒有半獸人這種東西
And now? How many have you killed?
現在呢？妳殺過多少？
-Many. -Good.
–很多 –很好
I would not use such words.
我不會這麼說
Why not?
為什麼？
It darkens the heart, to call dark deeds "good."
稱讚邪惡行為“很好” 會讓人心變得陰暗
It gives place for evil to thrive inside us.
會讓邪惡趁隙在我們內心滋長
Every war is fought both without and within.
每一場戰爭身體與心靈都在作戰
Of that, every soldier must be mindful.
這一點，每位戰士都必須牢記
Even I. Even you.
我也是，你也是
Am I a soldier, then?
所以我是戰士囉？
Perhaps we can make one of you yet.
或許我們能讓你成為戰士
How much further until we reach the encampment?
還要走多久才會到營地？
It's just beyond this rise.
再過一個山頭就到了
How much further until we're clear of this smoke?
還要走多久煙霧才會散去？
Hold here.
停下來
How long have we been clear of it?
已經散去多久了？
Nearly a mile.
差不多一里
I see.
這樣啊
Do you?
還好嗎？
Only gray.
一片灰暗
Keep walking, both of you.
繼續往前走
Guide my horse. No one need notice.
牽好我的馬，別讓人發現
Elendil?
伊蘭迪爾？
Elendil, please.
伊蘭迪爾，麻煩你
Keep walking.
繼續往前走
They call it Greenwood the Great.
這裡人稱巨綠森林
Keep your head down and your eye on that line of cliffs.
低頭沿著那面懸崖找
You'll find the big folk settlements on the far side.
你會看到遠處有大種人的村落
With any luck, the people there can help you find your stars.
運氣好的話 說不定他們能幫你找你的星星
'Cause all I can tell you is,
因為我只能跟你說
Harfoot-folk haven't seen 'em
毛腳族從沒看過這些星星
since the days our ancestors lived in parts unknown
我們的祖先一千多年來都居住在
over a thousand years ago.
看不到這些星星的地方
And that's a long time to wander. Even for a fellow with big legs.
要想看到要走很長的路 就算有大長腿也一樣
Should've just stayed on-trail.
我不該偏離軌道的
When I saw that star falling, I should've just let it alone.
當時看到那顆星星墜落 我應該不管它的
-Elanor... -You tried to tell me, Mother.
–艾拉諾… –妳一直耳提面命，母親
But now I understand.
現在我明白了
I'm just a Harfoot.
我只是個毛腳族
That's all I'll ever be.
就該安分守己
Off to bed, Nori.
先睡吧，諾瑞
We can tend to the rest in the mornin'.
剩下的明早再處理
Have you ever lost someone close?
妳失去過親人嗎？
To them?
因為他們？
Kin, I mean.
我是說家人
My brother. Finrod.
我哥哥，芬羅德
And my husband.
還有我丈夫
Husband?
丈夫？
Celeborn was his name.
他的名字是凱勒鵬
We met in a glade of flowers.
我們在一片花海中相遇
I was dancing and he saw me there.
我當時翩翩起舞，他看到了我
You were dancing?
妳翩翩起舞？
The war seemed so very far away then.
那時戰爭感覺好遙遠
When he went to it, I chided him.
有天他準備上戰場，我責備他
His armor didn't fit properly.
他的戰甲不太合身
I called him a silver clam.
我笑他是一隻銀色蛤蜊
I never saw him again after that.
那是我最後一次看到他
My lady.
夫人
What you said before...
妳之前說的…
You're wrong.
妳錯了
It isn't your fault.
這不是妳的錯
It's mine.
是我的錯
You did not intend for this to happen.
你不是故意的
I gave power to the enemy. So that makes me responsible.
我給了敵人力量，所以是我的責任
Some say that is the way of things.
有人會這麼說
But I believe the wise also look upon what is in our hearts.
但我相信智者也會審視我們的內心
And this was not in yours.
這不是你的本意
Do not take the burden of this day upon your shoulders, Theo.
西奧，別把今天這個重擔 加諸在你的肩上
You may find it difficult to put it down again.
你會發現要再放下難上加難
But how am I to let it go?
可是我要怎樣才能釋懷？
There are powers beyond darkness at work in this world.
在這個世界上 有超越黑暗的力量在運作
Perhaps on days such as this,
或許在這樣的日子裡
we've little choice but to trust to their designs.
我們只能選擇相信他們的安排
And surrender our own.
放下我們的執著
My home is gone.
我的家毀了
Where's the design in that?
這算什麼安排？
I cannot yet see it.
我現在還看不明白
-Stop.
大人…
Shut it.
安靜
What is it? What do you smell?
怎麼了？你聞到什麼味道？
Ashes.
灰燼
Nothin' but ashes.
一片灰燼
Come on. We're wasting time.
走吧，別浪費時間了
Rest while you can.
把握時間休息一下
We move at first light.
天一亮我們就動身
What light?
哪來的天亮？
Another tremor.
又地震了
We need to give the rocks time to resettle.
我們得給岩層一點時間重新排列
Self-discipline, master Elf.
自律，精靈大人
Think that'll bring you success?
那是你成功的祕訣？
It did in our contest.
在我們之前的比賽確實如此
Did it?
是嗎？
No.
不會吧
You lost on purpose?
你故意輸給我？
My aim was never to defeat you,
我的目標從來不是打敗你
but to gain your ear a while longer.
而是讓你願意聽我說話
Elf lies.
精靈騙人精
I was...
我當時的確…
Winded.
喘不過氣來
Blast it.
該死
I always thought you were a mite Dwarvish for an Elf.
我一直覺得你這精靈有點像矮人
And you are a rather Elvish Dwarf, Durin.
你這矮人也滿像精靈的，都靈
-Son of Durin.
都靈之子
-Grandson of... -Scoff if you like.
–都靈之孫… –愛怎麼笑隨便你
The mightiest thing a Dwarf can do is to be worthy of the name of his father.
一個矮人最偉大的成就 就是配得上自己父親的名字
We do have our secret names,
我們其實有秘密小名
for use only amongst ourselves.
只會在自己人之間使用
And we reveal them only to family.
也只會告訴家人
Wives, parents, sisters, brothers.
妻子、父母、姊妹、兄弟
-Elrond... -Save it, Durin.
–愛隆… –先別說，都靈
For the far side.
等成功了再說
Aye.
好
Durin...
都靈…
Father...
父王…
It's more than we ever imagined.
比我們想像得還要大量
-King Durin, there is a... -Enough!
–都靈國王，有… –夠了！
Father, just look at it.
父王，你自己看看
Seize the Elf.
將精靈打入大牢
When your mother bore you,
你剛出生時
something inside you was ill-formed.
帶了某種天生缺陷
Your breathing was ragged and dry.
呼吸急促又乾澀
A tiny, pitiful sound, like scraping chalkstones.
小小的聲音聽起來好可憐 像是在刮著石灰岩
Folk said you'd never see your first winter.
人們說你活不過第一個冬天
And every night,
每天晚上
after your mother's weeping eyes had found refuge in sleep,
在你母親哭累了入睡之後
I held you to the firelight,
我會抱著你在爐火旁
kept your chin up all night long.
整晚抬著你的下巴
Seemed to ease the burden a little.
感覺能減輕一點你的痛苦
And one night,
有天晚上
I gazed down on your tiny, naked face,
我盯著你光溜溜的小臉蛋
and I saw upon it
依稀看見了
the great gray beard of an old Dwarven-king.
矮人族先王的偉大灰鬍
Mighty and terrible as an army with banners.
強大威武 猶如一支高舉旌旗的大軍
And when your mother woke, I told her,
等你母親醒來，我告訴她
she need cry no more.
她無須再掉淚了
Our son would live and he would move mountains!
我們的兒子會活下來 他將撼動群山！
How do you expect me to move mountains, Father,
父王，你怎能期望我撼動群山
if you fall to pieces when I dig a single hole?
我不過挖個洞你就大抓狂？
You speak of greatness for me,
你口口聲聲要我成就非凡
but you suffocate in me any ambition,
卻扼殺我所有抱負
any desire,
所有渴望
any thought that does not originate in you.
所有想法，只要跟你意見相左
The iron that must bear the most heavy of burdens
不經沉重考驗、嚴酷磨練
must also endure the most rigorous tempering!
怎能煉就堅實鋼鐵！
Consigning your allies to death is not tempering.
眼睜睜看盟友去死不叫磨練
Elrond is as much a brother to me
愛隆對我來說親如兄弟
as if he'd been fired in my own mother's womb.
就好像從同一母親肚裡蹦出來那樣
How dare you...
你竟敢…
How dare you!
你好大的膽子！
Invoke your mother's memory
竟然用你母親的回憶
to defend your decision to betray your own kind?
為你背叛族人的行為辯護？
No! It's you that's betrayed our kind!
錯了！背叛族人的人是你！
Squandering our future so you can cling to the past!
執著於過去，揮霍我族的未來！
You profane the crown you wear!
你對不起你頭上戴的王冠！
Leave it.
不准碰
It's not yours anymore.
那不再屬於你了
And while he was a snailin'
就在那個秋日 當他抓著蝸牛時
His babe he left a-wailin' The stream took her away
他哭泣的寶寶 被那溪流帶走啦
-Poppy? -Hmm?
波皮？妳在幹嘛？
Fetchin' a pail, what's it look like?
拿桶子啊，不然呢？
No, the vittles. Stop eatin'! We have to save those.
別吃了！我們要省吃儉用
Why don't you take a look outside, and then we'll talk.
妳先看看外面，再來跟我說
What...
什麼鬼
Look at that! Oh, wow!
–你瞧瞧！哇！ –可以拿去賣…
Here you go.
來
I don't understand. How?
我不懂，怎麼會？
How do you think?
妳覺得呢？
He fixed it.
他的功勞
Can you believe it, Nori?
諾瑞，妳敢相信嗎？
There's enough bounty here to feast tonight
這些食物夠我們今晚大吃一頓
and still have enough left over to last to Frozen Fish.
還夠我們一路吃到凍魚地
Malva's sayin' she gonna make somethin' called apple-sausage.
馬爾娃說她會做一種 叫蘋果腸的東西
-Applesauce. -That's what I said.
–是蘋果醬 –我就是這麼說的
From Father.
父親給的
Thank you, Malva. Where's your sister gone?
馬爾娃，謝謝，妳妹哪去了？
We got it. Is there more space in there? We're done.
好了，那邊還有空間嗎？這裡滿了
...floated down it So loudly she did wail
…她哭得好大聲
The King of the Frog Fishies
青蛙魚國王
Turned her into a snail
把她變蝸牛
Old Bolgerbuck he caught her So juicy and so sweet
老皮革哥抓到了她 多汁又甜美
They say his little daughter He could not help but...
他們說是他寶貝女兒 他卻忍不住…
You're going the wrong way.
你走錯邊了
He went that way.
他往那邊去了
Go on, now.
去啊
Nori!
諾瑞！
-Leave her alone! -You heard her.
–放開她！ –聽到她說的了
-Off with you now! -Begone!
–快給我滾！ –滾！
You harm a hair on her foot, and I'll brain the lot of ya.
敢傷她一根腳毛，我砸爛你們的頭
Come on. All right. Keep your hands on.
來，好，把手放在…
Together now.
用力
Whoa!
冷靜！
Give him to me.
我來吧
No!
不行！
You're going home. Do you hear me?
乖乖回家，聽到沒？
You're coming with us.
跟我們回家
Please. Berek.
別這樣，貝雷克
-Please. -He won't listen to you.
–拜託了 –牠不會聽你的話
He won't listen to any of us.
牠不會聽我們任何人的話
I should never have pulled the Elf on board.
我真不該拉那精靈上船
I should've left her in the sea, where I found her.
當時就該把她留在海上
Theo?
西奧？
The Queen Regent. Is she here?
攝政女王，她在嗎？
Preparations are nearly complete.
差不多已準備妥當
We can depart within the hour.
一小時內便可啟程
What of the Southlanders?
那些南地人怎麼辦？
One garrison will remain behind to escort them to a safe settlement.
我們會派人留守 護送他們到安全的地方
And search for our missing.
同時搜尋我方失蹤人員
Galadriel.
凱蘭崔爾
No one kneels in Númenor.
在努曼諾爾沒人需要下跪
You are not in Númenor.
這裡不是努曼諾爾
Neither of you are.
你們身在異鄉
A fault that is mine alone.
這一切都是我的錯
Our ships are waiting, my Queen.
船隊在等候出發，女王
Let us put this land behind our sails.
離開這片土地，揚帆而去吧
Do not spend your pity on me, Elf.
別把妳的憐憫浪費在我身上，精靈
Save it for our enemies.
留給我們的敵人吧
For they do not know what they have begun.
他們不知道自己挑起了 什麼樣的戰爭
For I, Míriel,
我，密瑞爾
daughter of Ar-Inziladûn, vow this.
亞爾印西拉頓之女，在此立誓
Númenor will return.
努曼諾爾會捲土重來
Then the Elves will be ready.
精靈族也會準備就緒
Captain, we sail with the tide.
船長，我們儘快出發吧
Captain?
船長？
I got it.
我來
On your feet now, girl. Stand up. Help me gather what we can.
動起來，ㄚ頭，站起來 幫我採集多少算多少
Nori, now.
諾瑞，快點
Don't let this splinter your spirit, it'll be all right.
不要這樣就被打倒 一切都會好起來的
Don't lie to her, Largo. She's too old for that now.
不要騙她，拉哥，她已經長大了
I wasn't lyin'. It will be all right.
我沒騙她，一切都會好起來的
Pity's sake, Brandyfoot.
拜託，白蘭地足
Give us a moment to weep.
給大家一點時間哀傷
Weepin'?
哀傷？
Is that all you think we have left in us?
你以為我們只剩這條路可走？
We're Harfoots!
我們是毛腳族耶
Look, we don't slay dragons.
我們不會殺惡龍
Not much for diggin' jewels.
也不會挖寶石
But there's one thing we can do, I warrant,
但有件事我們很擅長
better than any creature in all Middle-earth.
比中土世界任何生物都厲害
We stay true to each other.
我們忠於彼此
No matter how the path winds, or how steep it gets,
無論前方道路多麼曲折、多麼陡峭
we face it,
我們勇敢面對
with our hearts even bigger than our feet.
我們的勇氣比我們的大腳還要驚人
And we just keep walkin'.
勇往直前就對了
Nori. Where are you goin'?
諾瑞，妳要去哪？
To help my friend.
去幫助我的朋友
Warn him what's comin'. He deserves at least that.
去警告他要小心，這是最起碼的吧
Goin' off-trail? Now? Alone?
妳現在要偏離軌道？一個人？
She won't be alone.
她不會一個人
We've left enough folk behind, we're not leavin' him.
我們丟下夠多人了，不能再丟下他
You girls aren't goin' anywhere.
妳們兩個哪裡都別想去
Not without me.
除非我一起去
You sure about this, Goldie?
妳確定嗎，戈蒂？
You go into those woods, you might never come out alive.
一旦走進那樹林 就可能無法活著出來
They might if a trail-finder were to go with them.
有人帶路就有機會
Brandyfoot girl was right to help him. Was right all along.
白蘭地足家的ㄚ頭幫助他是對的 一直都是對的
And if you think Malva Meadowgrass is too proud to admit it,
如果你覺得 馬爾娃太過驕傲不想承認
well, what's the good of livin', Sadoc, if we aren't livin' good?
那薩道克，如果不為仁善而活 活著還有什麼意義？
You know, Malva, just once...
馬爾娃，一次就好
Once, it would be grand if you weren't right all the time.
如果妳不要每次都那麼有道理 那該有多好
I'll fetch provisions and get me stick.
我去帶上糧食和拐杖
I'm comin' with ya.
我跟你們去
It doesn't matter anyway, we're all gonna die.
沒差啦，反正人終究一死
Come on, otherwise we'll be here all day.
快點，整天都要耗掉了
Think we'll be able to find him?
我們真能找到他嗎？
He's a bloody giant. How could we miss him?
他塊頭這麼大，怎麼可能找不到？
You believe she'll keep her promise?
妳相信她會信守承諾？
No.
不
I'm certain of it.
我確定她會
Bones have been set, wounds bound. We can travel.
骨折已固定好，傷口已包紮好 可以啟程了
Where will you go?
你們要去哪？
An old Númenórean colony by the mouth of the Anduin.
努曼諾爾在安都因河口 一處舊殖民地
Pelargir,  they called it. They say there's fresh land, fresh water.
他們稱之為佩拉格 他們說那裡有新土和活水
A fresh start.
全新的開始
Then I will report to our High King.
那我去稟告精靈至高王
To face whatever awaits me.
面對等待著我的一切
But what of our king?
那我們的國王怎麼辦？
Your king?
你們的國王？
Has no one informed you?
沒人告訴妳嗎？
Informed me of what?
告訴我什麼？
Halbrand.
賀爾布蘭
I thought you had died.
我以為你死了
Better for me if I had done.
死了可能還比較好
Southlanders found him on the road like this yestereve.
南地人昨晚在路邊發現他
The wound soured overnight.
一夜之間傷口惡化了
I thought to try and treat him on the road, but...
我本來想在路上幫他治療，但…
This wound needs Elvish medicine.
他的傷口需要精靈的藥物
Can he ride?
他能騎馬嗎？
I'll have the healers gather what provisions they can.
我去請治療師盡力收集物資
Well, my friend.
我的朋友
It seems fate has in store for us one more raft.
看來命運又為我們準備了一艘木筏
This is not over.
還沒結束
I will not abandon these lands and condemn them to burn.
我不會拋棄這片土地 任其付之一炬
Nor will you.
妳也不行
Strength to the king!
天佑國王！
Keep it... Soldier.
留著吧，戰士
Commander.
指揮官
Strength to the Southlands!
天佑南地人！
I failed him.
我讓他失望了
It's all my fault.
全都是我的錯
No.
不是
No, it isn't.
不是的
Whose is it, then?
那是誰的錯？
It's your father's.
錯的是你父王
He's grown too old, too suspicious.
他老了，變得太多疑
His mind, too feeble.
他的心智變得太衰弱
His eyes too dim to see
他的雙眼變得太模糊而看不清
that no matter how many crests he hurls to the floor,
無論他摔過多少家徽到地上
one day this will be your kingdom.
有一天這王國將屬於你
Durin IV's.
都靈四世
Not your brother's.
不屬於你的兄弟
Not some other Dwarf-lord's. Yours.
不屬於其他矮人領主，屬於你
And mine.
也屬於我
And together, we will rule this mountain and all others before our time is done.
我們將攜手統治群山 直到我們的時代結束
That  mithril  belongs to us.
秘銀屬於我們
To you and me.
屬於你我
And together, one day,
終有一天
we are going to dig.
我們將一同開採
Seal it up.
封存吧
My children.
孩子們
Cast off your sun-cloaks and your helms.
脫下你們的斗篷和頭盔
You are no longer to be burdened by the day.
你們無須再為白日所苦
This is our land now.
這片土地現在屬於我們
It is our home.
這裡是我們的家園
Hail Adar, Lord of the Southlands!
南方大地之主，阿達爾萬歲！
No...
不對
That is the name of a place that no longer exists.
南方大地已不存在
What should we call it instead, Lord-father?
那我們該取名為什麼呢，父親大人？
Adar! Adar!
阿達爾！